Finding Aid for Department of Physiology (University of Michigan) records, 1884-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Physiology (University of Michigan) records 1884-1979
University of Michigan. Department of Physiology.
87163 Bimu C46 2
Files of Professors John W. Bean, Robert Gesell, Warren P. Lombard, and Henry Sewall, 1925-1979; miscellaneous departmental papers relating to the Hyperbaric Chamber Committee, the Institute for Human Adjustment, the Lombard Library, research funds, and teaching assignments; and publications of physiological laboratory; and collection of physiology textbooks, manuals, and monographs, mainly written by University of Michigan faculty; also photographs and films.
3 linear feet
1 oversize boxes
1 film reels
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the Department of Physiology (Donor No. 6849 ) in various accessions beginning in 1982.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open to research.
The origins of physiology at the University of Michigan can be traced to the Organic Act of 1837 establishing the university. This act included provisions for a professorship in physiology within the Department of Medicine and Surgery. Physiology was one of four subjects required for graduation of the first class of medical students. The first physiology course was taught in 1850 by Jonathan A. Allen, one of the five original members of the medical department. Upon his resignation in 1854, the medical faculty was reorganized and Abram Sager, the first president of the faculty of the Department of Medicine and Surgery and later dean of the Medical School, was appointed professor of physiology (Professor of Obstetrics and Physiology, Botany and Zoology, 1854; Professor of Obstetrics and Physiology, 1855-1860; Professor of Obstetrics and Diseases of Women and Children, 1860-1875).
Other early prominent professors of physiology at the University of Michigan included Corydon L. Ford, Henry Sewall, and Warren Plimpton Lombard. Corydon L. Ford (Professor of Anatomy, 1854; Professor of Anatomy and Physiology, 1860-1894), although an anatomist, recognized the importance of laboratory work to physiology and urged the administration to establish a physiological laboratory and to appoint a permanent professor on the subject. The modern program of experimental physiology at the university began in 1881 with the appointment of Henry Sewall (Lecturer, 1881; Professor of Physiology, 1882-1888). Sewall was instrumental in the development of the Physiological Laboratory, leading to the first laboratory course in physiology offered in any medical school in the country. Warren Plimpton Lombard (Professor of Physiology and Histology, 1892-1898; Professor of Physiology, 1898-1923) continued to improve upon the physiology laboratory course and to purchase more equipment. By 1904 this laboratory course was required of all medical and homeopathic students.
The first chairman of the Department of Physiology was Robert Gesell, appointed in 1923 (Professor of Physiology, 1923-1954). During his tenure, Gesell oversaw the department's move into the newly constructed East Medical Building and recruited new instructors from the graduate students within the department. Upon the death of Gesell in 1954, John W. Bean was appointed Acting Chair until the arrival of Horace W. Davenport in 1956.
The chairmanship of Horace Willard Davenport (1956-1978) was a period of great growth and refinement for the department. The department grew four times in size, and federal research funds increased steadily. As a result of this growth, much attention was devoted to an examination of the physiology curriculum with courses and requirements being reevaluated and restructured. In 1969, the department was moved from the East Medical Building to the Medical Science II Building.
For further information on the history of the Department of Physiology, the researcher should consult both the Printed Catalog and the Manuscripts Catalog of the Bentley Historical Library. Related manuscript collections include the papers of former students William Aulls Campbell and Anna Marion Cooke, and the papers of Drs. Horace W. Davenport, Robert Gesell, and Warren P. Lombard.
Early Professors and Instructors of Physiology
1850-1854 Allen, Jonathan A., Jr.
1854-1860 Sager, Abram
1860-1894 Ford, Corydon L.
1872-1873 Cheever, Henry S.
1874-1875 Gerrish, Frederic H.
1876-1881 Ford, Corydon L.
1876-1877 Wilder, Burt G.
1876-1881 Stowell, Charles H.
1881-1888 Sewall, Henry
1889-1892 Howell, William Henry
1892-1923 Lombard, Warren Plimpton
1906-1911 Wiggers, Carl
Chairmen of Department of Physiology
1923-1954 Gesell, Robert
1954-1956 Bean, John W. (Acting Chair)
1956-1978 Davenport, Horace W.
1978-1979 Jochim, Kenneth (Acting Chair)
1979-1985 Kostyo, Jack L.
1985-1987 Jacquez, John A. (Acting Chair)
1987- Williams, John Andrew
The records of the Department of Physiology consist of 3 linear feet, 1 outsize box, and 1 outsize film, and cover the years 1884 to 1979. The records consist largely of the files of Professors John W. Bean, Robert Gesell, Warren P. Lombard, and Henry Sewall, 1925-1979. They include miscellaneous departmental papers relating to the Hyperbaric Chamber Committee, the Institute for Human Adjustment, the Lombard Library, research funds, and teaching assignments; and publications of physiological laboratory; and collection of physiology textbooks, manuals, and monographs, mainly written by University of Michigan faculty. The record group also includes photographs and films. The records are divided into three series: Topical Files, Faculty, and Audio and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute for Human Adjustment.; University of Michigan. Medical School.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bean, John William, 1901-1987.; Laboratories.; Meetings.
Contributors:
Bean, John William, 1901-1987.; Gesell, Robert, 1886-1954.; Lombard, Warren P. (Warren Plimpton), 1855-1939.; Sewall, Henry, 1855-1936.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Motion pictures.
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (.7 linear feet and 1 outsize box) consists of administrative records of the department, including budget materials, curricula and course materials, and departmental reviews and evaluations. Histories of the department have been placed at the beginning of Box 1 for the convenience of the researcher. Other historical materials relating to the department and faculty can be found in the Faculty series in the folder "John W. Bean, Reminiscences" and in the folders pertaining to Horace W. Davenport.
  - Histories of Department of Physiology (includes historical information on former faculty and staff) (Box 1)
  - Affirmative Action (recruitment of women and minorities)
    - General 1966-1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Black Medical Student Association and Physiology 500 1975 (Box 2)
  - Budget 1925-1957, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Building and Space Needs 1927-1977 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Curricula and Course Materials
    - General 1953-1977, undated (Box 1)
    - Demonstrations 1955/56, undated (Box 1)
    - Laboratory Course in Physiology, 1904/1905 (typed notes) (Box 1)
    - Physiology 320, Spring 1960, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Physiology 500
      - 1963-1976, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1978 Fall term (Box 1)
    - Student Experiment: Anticholinesterases 1953 (Box 1)
  - Hyperbaric Chamber Committee 1964 (Box 1)
  - Institute for Human Adjustment 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - Lombard Library 1923-1955 (Box 1)
  - Office procedures index file for secretaries 1955 (Box 1)
  - Personnel 1974, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Reprints and pamphlets collected by W.P. Lombard 1887-1930, undated (Box 1)
    (survey number 91-014)
  - Research Funds 1939-1948 (Box 1)
  - Reviews and Evaluations (departmental) 1960-1976, undated (Box 1)
  - Staff Meeting October 20, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Students
    - General 1967-1977 (Box 1)
    - Summer Training Program 1959-1962 (Box 1)
  - Summer Session 1960, 1963 (Box 1)
- Faculty
  The Faculty series (1.0 linear foot and 1 outsize box) consists of materials from former physiology professors John W. Bean, Horace W. Davenport, Robert Gesell, Warren P. Lombard, and Henry Sewall. These folders include biographical and historical materials, correspondence, research, lectures, and writings. The outsize box consists primarily of research results from work conducted by Warren P. Lombard during the years 1884 to 1910. The records are very fragile and include kymograph and plethysmograph records.
  - General 1950-1978, undated (includes historical materials) (Box 2)
  - Bean, John W.
    - Reminiscences (both biographical and departmental) undated (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1930-1957 (Box 2)
    - Professional and Research Activities
      - General 1950, 1964-1967, 1979 (Box 2)
      - Michigan Academy of Science 1942-1943 (Box 2)
      - Reprints 1929-1974 (Box 2)
        (survey number 91-016)
  - Davenport, Horace W.
    - Biographical and Personal 1929-1973 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1940-1977 (Box 2)
    - Speeches, Lectures, and Writings
      - General 1939, 1962-1982, undated (Box 2)
      - "The Life and Death of Laboratory Teaching of Physiology: A Personal Narrative," undated (Box 2)
  - Gesell, Robert
    - Biographical 1938, 1954 (Box 2)
    - Animal Welfare Institute 1952-1959 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - General 1922-1956, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Bohr, David F. 1937-1953 (Box 2)
      - Bronk, Detlev Wolf 1926-1942 (Box 2)
      - Brookhart, John M. 1939-1948 (Box 2)
      - Dontas, Anastasius 1946-1952 (Box 2)
      - Wiggers, Carl J. 1937-1949 (Box 2)
      - Zotterman, Yngre 1940-1949 (Box 2)
    - Speeches and Lectures 1939, 1950-1956, undated (Box 2)
  - Lombard, Warren P.
    - General 1890-1957 (Box 2)
    - Professional Activities 1901, 1907, 1938 (Box 2)
    - Research
      (see also outsize Box 4)
      - 1884 (Box 2)
      - 1896-1917, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Research (includes Kymograph and Plethysmograph Records) 1884-1910 (Box 4)
  - Sewall, Henry 1933-1936 (Box 2)
- Audio and Visual Materials
  The Audio and Visual Materials series (1.0 linear feet and 1 outsize film) is divided into three subseries: Photographs, Audiotapes, and Films.
  - Photographs
    The Photographs are from a wide range of years (late 1800s to 1979) and portray former faculty and staff and facilities. Additional photographs of European physiologists collected by Dr. Lombard are located in one folder in the outsize box.
    - Conferences, Hyperbaric 1964, circa 1966 (Box 3)
    - Faculty and Staff
      - Groups 1897, circa 1938-1958, 1964 (includes some negatives) (Box 3)
      - Individuals
        - General circa 1901, circa 1940 (Box 3)
        - Bean, John W. 1979 and earlier (Box 3)
    - Laboratories and Equipment circa 1900, 1925, 1950, 1971, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Lombard Library undated (includes negative) (Box 3)
    - Physiologists, mostly European, late 19th century and early 1900s, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Physiologists and Anatomists, European circa 1890 (Box 4)
  - Audiotapes
    The Audiotapes subseries consists of 2 reel-to-reel tapes of a lecture given by Dr. Carl Wiggers in 1951 at the reunion of the Medical Class of 1906.
    - Wiggers, Dr., (Tape of lecture to Medical Class of 1906 reunion) 1951, 2 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes (Box 3)
  - Films
    The subseries of Films consists of .7 linear feet of films in Box 3 and 1 outsize film located separately. The films are arranged in the contents list by Survey Number. Prior to the transfer of the films to the Bentley Historical Library, the films were located at the university's Historical Center for the Health Sciences (HCHS). HCHS assigned a Survey Number to each film for purposes of maintaining their own database. A computer printout of the database records for these films, arranged by Survey Number, is attached to the end of the contents list. The researcher should consult the printout of database records for a more detailed description of each film.
    - Medical School Function, late 1940s, [92-015]; approx. 10 minutes, black and white, 16 mm, silent] (Box 3)
      (Records the people attending an outdoor medical school luncheon. Typical of a home movie in which the photographer randomly selects images of interest. Comes with a list of people presumably in order of appearance on camera. Of interest is the panning of the grounds and how the function is set up-typical of the 1940s if not appropriate for today.)
    - University of Michigan Alumni Reunion 1958, [92-016]; approx. 40 minutes, color, 16 mm, silent] (Reel 1)
      (This film taken by Roland Burd (Burck?) captures the various doctors and alumni that attended the Alumni Reunion of 1958. (approx 40 min.)
      (outsize, located separately)
    - "The Adrenal as a Contributor to the Stress of High O2," circa 1950s, [92-018]; approx. 15 minutes, black and white, 16 mm, silent] (Box 3)
      (This film produced by J. W. Bean and C. W. Smith, is a record of a NIH grant study on the effects of very high (80-90 lbs) 02 on rats. The film includes still photos of damaged organs placed in front of placards and footage of rats suffering from paralysis and mental confusion.)
    - "South American Furlough I"--Graceliner/ Peru 1941, [92-019]; approx. 25 minutes, color, 16 mm, silent] (Box 3)
      (see insert in film canister for detailed description)
      (Silent "home movie". This film is series of short scenes spliced together recording the South American trip taken by J. W. Bean. Scenes include shots of the local residents and beautiful landscapes. There is an extensive listing of the scenes included with the film by Mr. Bean.)
    - "South American Furlough II"--Buenos Aires to Rio de Janiero 1941, [92-020]; approx. 25 minutes, black and white,16 mm, silent] (Box 3)
      (Silent "home movie" This is the second film in a series produced by J. W. Bean. recording his trip to South America. He included a list of the scenes filmed with this reel also.)
    - "South American Furlough III"--Bu Tan Tan and Rio de Janiero 1941, [92-021]; approx 20 minutes, color, 16 mm, silent] (Box 3)
      (Silent "home movie". This is the last in a series of films by J W. Bean. Included in this reel are scenes from Bu Tan Tan snake farm and the San Paulo Medical School in Rio De Janiero. Finally the purpose of this trip is explained as he meets with two De Ahneida brothers who have been using high pressure 02 to treat human patients with cancer. There is a list of scenes included.)
    - "Chronic and Permanent Disabilities Induced by Exposure to O2 at High Pressure," circa 1950s, [92-022]; approx. 20 minutes, black and white, 16 mm, silent] (Box 3)
      (This film. produced by J. W. Bean and Ernest C. Siegfried records the effects of high pressure 02 on rats. Motor disability, hind leg paralysis, and mental confusion are among the effects studied.)
    - "Dr. Bean's Gassed Chickens," circa 1950s, [92-023]; approx. 15 minutes, color, 16 mm, silent] (Box 3)
      (Silent Experimental film in color. Another one of J. W. Bean's experimental films recording the effects of high pressure oxygen (OHP) This time the subject of the film is chickens and they experience the same kind of paralysis and disorientation as the rats.)
    - "Dr. Bean's Gassed Chicken Feathers," circa 1950s, [92-024]; approx. 5 minutes, color, 16 mm, silent] (Box 3)
      (This film by Dr. Bean is just a collection of still shots of chicken feathers.)
    - Home Movies of Dr. J. W. Bean circa 1950s, [92-025]; 3 reels; 16 mm, color] (Box 3)
      (Niagara Falls-Vacation scenes of Niagara falls and family; 11-Dorothy, Tommy, and Baby-More scenes of family and Niagara Falls. Also shots of chickens in the front yard of a home suffering the paralysis of high 02; Ill Dr. Bean's Family--Shots of Dr. Bean's family, (Mother, Father, etc.). Film is upside down.
    - Experiments of Dr. J. W. Bean on adult rats 1950-1951, [92-037]; 2 reels; 16 mm, black and white] (Box 3)
      (research films taken by Dr. Bean, 1950-51)
    - Experiments of Dr. J. W. Bean on rats circa 1960, [92-039]; 16 mm, black and white] (Box 3)
- Publications
  The Department of Physiology Publications contains a history of the Department written on the occasion of the centennial in 1982.
  - 100 Years of Physiology at Michigan, 1982 (Box 3)